<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A revelation of the Revelation wherein is contayned, a most true, plaine, and briefe manifestation of the meaning and scope of all the Reuelation, and of euery mystery of the same : whereby the pope is most plainely declared and proued to bee Antichrist / by Thomas Mason ...</title>
            <author>Mason, Thomas, 1580-1619?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1299</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22106383</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22106383</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07226)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1732:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A revelation of the Revelation wherein is contayned, a most true, plaine, and briefe manifestation of the meaning and scope of all the Reuelation, and of euery mystery of the same : whereby the pope is most plainely declared and proued to bee Antichrist / by Thomas Mason ...</title>
                  <author>Mason, Thomas, 1580-1619?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 102 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By G. Eld,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸ H².</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 82 misnumbered 80.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25079:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REVELATION OF THE <hi>REVELATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is contayned, a moſt true, plaine, and briefe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the meaning and ſcope of all the Reuelation, and of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Myſtery of the ſame:</p>
            <p>Whereby the Pope is moſt plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared and proued to bee Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>BY THOMAS MASON Preacher of the word of God at Odyham in the County of South.</p>
            <p>Printed at London by <hi>G. Eld.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:25079:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25079:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HIGH AND MIGHTY, KING IAMES, by the eſpeciall Grace of God, of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, and in all cauſes, whether Eccleſiaſticall or Ciuill, next vnder CHRIST ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Head, and a moſt faithfull De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender of the true Catholique and Apoſtolique Faith, in all his <hi>Realmes and Dominions;</hi> Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplyed.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Excellent Soueraigne:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing attained vnto ſome cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of the ſcope and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation,</hi> and of the Myſteries
<pb facs="tcp:25079:3"/>thereof, by earneſt prayer, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vſing of Expoſitors, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of the Propheſies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories; and being deſirous to inlighten others, I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled, in as briefe and eaſie manner as I could deuiſe, the true ſcope and meaning of the ſame, and of euery Myſterie thereof: And being well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that as God gaue vnto the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> a rich meaſure of his Spirit, ſo he hath bequeathed vnto your Highneſſe moſt abundantly, his holy Ghoſt: ſo that none more knoweth the minde of Chriſt then you Maieſty doth.
<pb facs="tcp:25079:3"/>Which imboldened me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate this my Worke vnto your Highneſſe, moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crauing, that this little ſhew of my dutifull loue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maieſtie, may obtaine pardon for my too much boldneſſe: ſo, as it is my boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den dutie, I will neuer ceaſe to offer vppe ſupplications vnto God and vnto Ieſus Chriſt, for the dewe of his Spirit to be daily diſtilled in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Royall heart, for your direction, and that God would alwayes charge his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels for the preſeruation of your Maieſties perſon, and of our moſt gracious Queene,
<pb facs="tcp:25079:4"/>our moſt Royall Prince, and all your Highneſſe Kingly Progenie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Maieſties</hi> moſt faithfull and dutifull Subiect, THOMAS MASON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25079:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (Chriſtian Reader) I would haue thee to obſerue in the three firſt Chapters, the then preſent eſtate of the ſeauen Churches: and in the fourth and fifth Chapters, the viſion of Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in Heauen, in what manner hee receiued the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Reuelation from Chriſts aſcenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vntill his comming vnto iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: in the ſixt and ſeauenth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the eſtate of the Church vnder the Idolatrous Emperours, vntill the
<pb facs="tcp:25079:5"/>Chriſtian Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his time, and the flouriſhing of the eſtate thereof by him; and in the eighth, ninth, and tenth Chapters, the eſtate of the Church vnder the Emperors that were after <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> and the Popes: how men became as cold as hayle in true Religion, and as hot as fire to maintaine ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the ſhedding of blood: and how the Emperours, ſignified by the great Mountaine, tooke part with the ſuperſtitious, with a burning zeale perſecuting thoſe that would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to their ſuperſtitions.</p>
            <p>The great Starre that fell from Heauen as bitter as worme-wood, was the falling of the Biſhop of Rome from Chriſt and his word, to maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuperſtitions, and for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was exalted of the Emperours aboue all other Biſhops: The ſecond Starre is the Popes, which exalted themſelues aboue all the Emperours and Kings, and filled the world with
<pb facs="tcp:25079:5"/>their mighty Locuſts, that is, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls, Popiſh Biſhops, and their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Abbots, Friers, and ſuch like: and when theſe were multiplied, as the ſands of the ſea, the Diuell that was bound for a thouſand yeares, from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> his time, is let looſe, &amp; obtaineth theſe innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Locuſts to take his part, and perſecuted the Saints, &amp; by theſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Locuſts, martyred more then euer hee did by the idolatrous Emperours, yet Chriſt and his Saints obtaine the victory. And from the beginning of the eleuenth Chapter vnto the end of the Booke, are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied againe the very ſame things of Antichriſt: but much more large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with other ſimilitudes.</p>
            <p>In the eleuenth Chapter, the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious are called the Courts, and the faithfull the temple, and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is commanded, not to mete the Courts but to caſt them out, and it is prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied that they ſhall tread the holy Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:25079:6"/>which is the faithfull, vnder their feete, <hi>1260.</hi> yeares.</p>
            <p>In the twelfth Chapter, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours which before are called a great mountaine, are heere called a great red Dragon, and are propheſied to be they which ſhall be the greateſt cauſe of the treading vnder foote the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, all this time of the <hi>1260.</hi> yeares.</p>
            <p>In the thirteenth Chapter, the Popes that were called two Starres before, are called two beaſts: the firſt Beaſt the Emperours ſhall ſet aboue all other Biſhops, of purpoſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſuperſtitions, and to tread the faithfull vnder their feete all the ſaid time of <hi>1260.</hi> yeares, and for this purpoſe the Dragon ſhall giue him his power and authority.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Beaſt which had two hornes like the Lambe, is the ſecond Starre as before, which is the Pope, when hee tooke vpon him not onely to bee the whole ruler in ſpirituall
<pb facs="tcp:25079:6"/>matters, but to bee King of all Kings, as Chriſt is, and exalted himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the Emperours.</p>
            <p>All the other Chaptors vnto the end, declare the manner of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Antichriſt, and of Rome, and the flouriſhing of the Goſpell after Rome ſhall be deſtroyed vntill Chriſts comming to iudgement.</p>
            <p>As Chriſt foretolde the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieauſalem, and truely at his time appointed performed it; ſo ſurely bath Chriſt Propheſied, and as truely in his time will accompliſh the deſtruction of Rome: and as a whole yeare before the deſtruction of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, there was ſeene an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Blazing Starre; ſo the Blazing Starre that now ſo ſtrangely appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ſeemeth to manifeſt Gods fiery indignation againſt Rome, which ſhall ſhortly deſtroy it, and to bee a forewarning vnto all men that they flye from her falſe Doctrines, leſt they be pertakers of her puniſhments,
<pb facs="tcp:25079:7"/>and that all Kings and the Children of God ſhould haue their hearts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed like the flaming Starre, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that abhominable Strumpet, to gather themſelues to battell againſt her, and burne her with fire.</p>
            <p>And becauſe euery one of Gods Children muſt claime by a liuely faith as perticular vnto himſelfe all the generall promiſes of Chriſt, ſo we ought to apply the generall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, euery one vnto his owne ſoule. Let vs therefore examine our hearts whether wee retaine there any Popoſh ſuperſtition, or ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any of Gods commandements vnrepented of; for againſt ſuch that will not repent, the Lords anger bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth like the blazing Starre.</p>
            <p>But if wee flie by true repentance and a liuely faith, and catch hold of the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, to waſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way our ſinnes, and of his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to couer our imperfections; then may wee with ioy looke vpon this bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb facs="tcp:25079:7"/>Starre, and prayſe God for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring his fierce wrath againſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt and ſinners, and for haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to reuenge the blood of his Saints, and that the time approacheth to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large and decke with his graces his Spouſe the Church, which ſhall bee vpon the deſtruction of Rome, that the number of the elect being ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, Chriſt may come to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and exalt vs vnto his eternall glory.</p>
            <p>And becauſe the more neere the Diuell ſeeth his time of eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to approach, the more hee ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth againſt Gods Children: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this flaming ſtarre muſt certifie vs, that euen now the Diuell by his priuie Counſellors the Ieſuites, is moſt buſily plotting and practiſing the destruction of all Protestant Kings and Countries, and it ought to prouoke vs to earneſt prayer vnto our chiefe Captaine Ieſus Chriſt, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found their enterpriſes, and to deſtroy
<pb facs="tcp:25079:8"/>them in the ſame ſuare which they haue laid for others.</p>
            <p>To the Prince of the Kings of the earth, that loued vs and waſhed vs from our finnes, and made vs Kings and Prieſts vnto God, to him bee all honour, glory and power now and for euermore. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:25079:8"/>
            <head>A REVELATION of the <hi>Reuelation.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ven as GOD ſo much loued faithfull <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that hee would not deſtroy <hi>Zodome,</hi> vntill hee had foretold him thereof, and likewiſe his cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Children Iſraell, that he would doe nothing but he would foretell them therof by his Prophets: Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe as Chriſt ſo loued his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that hee foretould them his Sufferings, Death, Reſurrection, Aſcenſion, and the comming of the holy Ghoſt, their troubles that they ſhould ſuffer for his name, the ſucceſſe of the Goſpell, the deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieruſalem, the glory that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:25079:9"/>they &amp; the faithful ſhould haue with him in Heauen, ſuch immeaſurable riches of his loue hath God ſhewed vnto his faithfull ones in theſe laſt ages, in ſhewing vnto them what ſhall happen vnto his Church from the bleſſed Aſcenſion of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt vntill his glorious comming to Iudgement.</p>
               <p>And becauſe he hath exalted Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt on his right hand, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all power vnto him in Heauen and earth, and made him the onely ſaluation of all that are or ſhalbe ſaued; hee hath likewiſe giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him this Reuelation: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Angels be his miniſtring ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits for our ſaluation, Chriſt hath ſent it by an Angell: and becauſe the Lord will not vſe the miniſtry of Angells immediatly for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, the Angell brought it to <hi>Iohn,</hi> to conuey it to the ſeauen Churches of Aſia, and although it is directed of God, onely to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:25079:9"/>ſeauen Churches of Aſia, it doth as properly belong to all Churches &amp; people of God as vnto them.</p>
               <p>In that it is ſaid to bee of things that ſhall ſhortly come to paſſe, a thouſand yeares with the Lord is but as one day with vs: In that they are pronounced bleſſed that read, heare, and keepe the things of this Prophecie, it ſhould ſtirre vs vp, neuer to be weary of knocking, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſeeking, vntill the true vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding here of be giuen vs; and this as the onely meanes, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> by his example commends vnto vs, in that hee beginneth with Prayer to the Father, Son and holy Ghoſt, for grace and peace for them.</p>
               <p>In that he calleth the holy Ghoſt which is one Spirit, ſeauen Spirits; it is in reſpect of the ſeauen folde operation therof in the 7. churches.</p>
               <p>And hauing now ſeene Ieſus Chriſt in heauen, hee cannot paſſe by him by barely naming him, but
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25079:10"/>declareth what hee hath ſeene of knowne of him; That he is a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witneſſe, the firſt begotten of the dead, Prince of the Kings of the earth, that loued vs and waſhed vs from our ſinnes with his bloud, and made vs Kings &amp; Prieſts vnto God: he commeth with clouds, and euery eye ſhall ſee him, yea, they that pierced him, and all kindreds of the earth ſhall wayle before him, euen ſo Amen.</p>
               <p>In that by perſecutions hee was faine to leaue his Churches, and to ſaue himſelfe in a deſolate place, he might think that God had forſaken his faithfull Churches, and him his faithfull ſeruant, but wee know that all things work for the beſt for Gods children; now euen now in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate place, he ſeeth more comfort then euer he did, and receiueth the greateſt Reuelation that euer was, and moſt beneficiall to the comfort and direction of the Church to the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25079:10"/>end of the world, and fends this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Churches farre paſſing the comfort of his preſence.</p>
               <p>In that the ſeauen golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtickes, which by Chriſt is inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted the ſeauen Churches, the gold thereof ſheweth the puritie of their Religion, without any droſſe of humane traditions or Iewiſh ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies.</p>
               <p>The office of a Candleſticke is to hold vp the candle, that it may ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten all the place where it is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is noted vnto vs, their care and loue of the Goſpell, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of others vnto the ſame, by holding vp and maintaining their Miniſters to edifie themſelues, and to bee a light to them that be in darkneſſe. And as Chriſt walked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt theſe golden Candleſticks, ſo wil he neuer be abſent from ſuch golden Candleſtickes.</p>
               <p>No man as he is fleſh and blood can ſee Chriſt as he is, therefore he
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25079:11"/>appeares vnto S. <hi>Iohn</hi> by viſion, and ſo no doubt hee did vnto S. <hi>Stephen</hi> when he ſaw the heauens open, and Chriſt ſitting at the right hand of God. Chriſts long garment &amp; gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den girdle was after the manner of Kings and Prieſts, &amp; declareth that he is the King of kings and Lord of lords, and the onely Ruler of all things in heauen and earth, and our onely high Prieſt. In his haire he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles auncient Senators, which ſheweth his wiſedome, and that he is the firſt and the laſt, <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> hee that was, and that is, and that is to come. His flaming eyes ſheweth that hee is the ſearcher of all reynes and hearts, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is hid from his eyes with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we haue to doe.</p>
               <p>His braſen feet declare that hee ſhall ſtampe the diuell and all his inſtruments, his and our enemies vnder his feet.</p>
               <p>His loud voyce manifeſteth that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25079:11"/>hee ſhall be heard vnto the end of the world, how forcible his Goſpel is to conuert the elect, how it ſhall be able to awake to life all that are dead, and to make the elect to meet him in the ayre, and to follow him vnto glory, and to caſt the diuell and all the wicked into hell.</p>
               <p>His two-edged Sword out of his mouth, ſheweth his wrath and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation vnto the enemies of his Church, and their deſtruction.</p>
               <p>His ſhining face ſheweth his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fauour vnto his children, and aſſureth them of his ſaluation.</p>
               <p>In that the Miniſters of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Churches are called Stars, they are ſhewed their office, euer to bee inlightning thoſe that are in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with the bright beames of the Goſpell, and to ſhew forth their loue vnto God and his children by their good workes, that men may glorifie their Father in heauen.</p>
               <p>In that he holds them in his hand,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:25079:12"/>whereas hee is ſaid but to be in the middeſt of the Candleſtickes, it aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſureth vs, if wee be ſuch Starres, he will haue a ſpeciall care ouer vs, he will hold vs in his hand, and none ſhall be able to hurt vs, or take vs from him.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Iohn</hi> at the firſt ſight did think him to be like Chriſt, but leſt hee ſhould be deceiued, Chriſt telleth him that He is he that was dead &amp; is aliue, and bade him behold him, and told him that he liued for euer, and had the keyes of hell and of death.</p>
               <p>In that <hi>Iohn</hi> is commanded to write theſe things, it ſheweth how neceſſary they are to be read of his Children: and in that Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreteth the hardeſt things to be vnderſtood in theſe viſions, it certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth vs, that wee may attaine vnto the meaning of all the reſt by ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt prayer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2 and 3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:25079:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>IN that Ieſus Chriſt commands <hi>Iohn</hi> to write ſeauen Letters vnto the ſeauen Churches, and indites euery Epiſtle with the words of his owne mouth, wee are aſſured that hee is the only head of the Church, and that his care and loue vnto the Church is no leſſe then when hee was vpon earth, and that hee ſeeth whatſoeuer is done, whether it be good or bad. Therefore let euery one of vs in his calling ſerue the Lord Ieſus, as walking alwayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his face: for ſuch an high Prieſt it behooued vs to haue, which is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, harmeleſſe, vndefiled, ſeperated from ſinners, and made higher then the heauens, and which once hath offered himſelfe a ſufficient ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for all the elect, and is conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for euermore.</p>
               <p>All Miniſters muſt ſtriue to ſerue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25079:13"/>Chriſt in thoſe things which hee commends in the Miniſters, for they concerne all Miniſters to the end of the world.</p>
               <p>The Miniſter of Epheſus is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for his workes, his labour, his patience, his zeale, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbeare the euill, but exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines falſe Apoſtles &amp; findes them lyars, and for ſuffring patiently for his name, and not fainting, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the workes of Seducers as the Nicholaitans.</p>
               <p>Hee ſaith to the Angell of the Church of Smyrna, I know thy workes, and thy labour, and pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but thou art rich.</p>
               <p>He ſaith vnto the Angell of the Church of <hi>Pergamus:</hi> I know thy workes and where thou dwelleſt, euen where Sathans throne is, and thou keepeſt my name, and haſt not denyed my faith, when <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pas</hi> my faithfull Martyr was ſlaine amongſt you.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:25079:13"/>
               <p>He ſaith to the Angell of <hi>Thya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyra</hi> I know thy workes, thy loue, and ſeruice, and faith &amp; patience, and thy works are more at laſt then at the firſt.</p>
               <p>If we follow theſe things vnto the end, we ſhall ouercome; then ſhall wee eat of the Tree of life in the midſt of Paradice, which is Chriſt; wee ſhall eate the Manna that is hid, which is the ioy of the holy Ghoſt, and peace of conſcience, wee ſhall haue a white ſtone and a new name, that wee are Chriſts written on it, which none can read but them which haue it, that is, the Spirit ſhall aſſure vs that wee are Gods Children, and none but our ſelues can know the aſſurance of our hope; then ſhall we haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to rule the Nations with a rod of Iron, that is, we ſhall ouercome the Diuell and ſinne, and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in the world to come breake them in pieces like a Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:25079:14"/>veſſell. As Chriſt receiued the morning ſtarre of his father, ſo he will giue it vs, that is, the ſpirit of wiſdome; wee ſhall be clothed in white, that is, with his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not bee put out of the booke of life, but Chriſt will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our names before his father and his Angells; we ſhall be made pillars in the temple of God, and goe out no more, and wee ſhall haue the name of our God, and the Citty of our God, and Chriſts new name written vpon vs, Chriſt will grant vs to ſit in his throne, as hee ſits in his fathers throne.</p>
               <p>In that the aduerſaries vnto the truth &amp; vnto Gods Miniſters are in the letter vnto the <hi>Smyrnians,</hi> &amp; in that to <hi>Philadelphia</hi> called the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Sathan, &amp; in the letter to <hi>Pergamus</hi> their dwelling is called the dwelling of Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; the throne of Sathan, and in the letter to <hi>Thia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyra,</hi> their falſe doctrine is called the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:25079:14"/>deepeneſſe of Sathan: let all ſuch know of whom they are, and call to God for his grace in Chriſt, that they may repent with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and be tranſlated from the power of Sathan into the Kingdome of Chriſt, neither needs Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Children bee afraid of them, their lies, ſubtile practiſes, or perſecutions, for he that is with vs is greater then he that is againſt vs.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe let all Gods Miniſters and Children marke what things the Miniſters are blamed for, that they may be wary not to offend in the ſame.</p>
               <p>Chriſt remembers the Angell of <hi>Epheſus</hi> that hee is fallen from the loue he had at the firſt, belike be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee reaped vnthankfulneſſe and ill will for his labour, this muſt not diſcourage vs, wee muſt looke for our reward of God, and if wee had neuer ſo many afflictions, they are not worthy of the great
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25079:15"/>glory wee ſhall haue in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Chriſt threatneth him to come againſt him ſhortly, and remoue his Candleſticke out of his place if he amend not; and ſurely this want of loue was it that remoued all theſe Candleſtickes out of their places, and long time theſe places haue beene inhabited of Idolaters.</p>
               <p>See what a many of commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vertues, euen of Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the Miniſter of <hi>Epheſus</hi> had, and loſt the reward of them all by looſing his loue, if hee did not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend.</p>
               <p>Chriſt findes fault with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of <hi>Pergamus</hi> for ſuffering the doctrine of <hi>Balaam,</hi> and of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholaitans</hi> to be maintained there, and threatneth to come againſt him for it, this muſt make vs wary not to ſuffer falſe doctrines to bee maintained.</p>
               <p>The Angell of <hi>Thiatyra</hi> is found fault with, for ſuffering <hi>Ieſabel</hi> to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:25079:15"/>intiſe Chriſts ſeruants to ſinne, we muſt take heed of ſuch.</p>
               <p>Chriſt findes fault with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of <hi>Sardis:</hi> that hee had a name that he liued, but he was dead: let vs therefore examine our ſelues well whether wee liue in the ſpirit, or be dead in any ſinne, and let vs awake and repent, elſe Chriſt will come vpon vs ſuddenly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy vs.</p>
               <p>Chriſt findes fault with the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of <hi>Laodicea</hi> becauſe hee was neither hot nor colde, and threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens to ſpue him out, and in that he boaſted of his riches and truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, ſaying that hee lacked nothing, and telleth him that hee was poore, and councelleth him to buy heauenly treaſure, and that hee was blinde, and willeth him to buy the eye ſalue of the ſpirit, that he might ſee the riches of Chriſt; and therefore for the want of Chriſts righteouſneſſe imputed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:25079:16"/>vnto him, was naked and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Chriſt telleth him that as many as hee hath he rebuketh and chaſteneth; and telleth him that he ſtands at the dore and knocks that is, at the heart, and if any heare and open, hee will come in and ſuppe with him, and he ſhall ſuppe with Chriſt, that is, Chriſt will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce to ſaue him, and hee will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce that he is ſaued of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In that Chriſt from heauen ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ſeauen Miniſters, and in them all other Minſters, by the name of Angels, it ſheweth, that he vſeth them the onely meanes to call the elect to grace, and it tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth Miniſters to looke to God and his word onely for their Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, and hearers to receiue the word preached as of God and not of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4 and 5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:25079:16"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.</head>
               <p>NOw this Viſion concerning the preſent eſtate of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Churches being ended, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> is taken vp into Heauen in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, to receaue a Reuelation from Heauen, touching the whole af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Church vnto the end of the world, but this was likewiſe directed to the ſeauen Churches, and therefore here the ſpirit is ſaid to be ſeuen ſpirits, &amp; Chriſt is ſaid to haue ſeuen hornes, that is, his power in euery Church.</p>
               <p>As S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> when hee was taken vppe into the third Heauen could not vtter that which hee ſaw and heard there, ſo no doubt it was with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn,</hi> but this viſion was ſhewed him for our intelligence.</p>
               <p>The things in ſumme which hee ſaw, was the inſpeakeable glory of God and Chriſt, &amp; all Angells and Saints, praiſing God for their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:25079:17"/>and hee ſaw Gods anger againſt the damned, by the voyces, thunders, lightenings and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes which hee ſaw in the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>God ſeemes to him like a King, ſitting in Parliament in his chaire of eſtate, with a Raine-bow com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing him, to glorifie him: his face like a <hi>Iaſper</hi> ſtone, and a <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine.</hi> But the glory of God is the truth of his promiſes, which is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by the Raine-bow, which was giuen to certifie vs of the truth of his promiſe, that hee would neuer drowne the World againe; and the face of the Lord is his louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto his children in Chriſt, which is ſignified in theſe moſt beautifull ſtones, the <hi>Sardine</hi> and the <hi>Iaſper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 24. Elders are the bookes of the law and the Prophets, the foure Beaſts are the foure Goſpells, theſe ſet forth his glory, and declare the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:25079:17"/>truth of his promiſes more then the Raine-bow, and the brightneſſe of his loue vnto his Children more then the <hi>Iaſper</hi> and <hi>Sardine</hi> ſtones.</p>
               <p>The Elders are cloathed in white, to ſhew the purity of their doctrine; they haue Crownes, to ſhew how powerfull they are to conuince ſin and error: theſe and the beaſts are about the throne, becauſe none come to God but by them: they ſit as Iudges, becauſe at the ende of the world all ſhall bee iudged by them.</p>
               <p>Theſe comforted Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> when he wept, ſo will they all of vs if wee ſeeke comfort of them, and if any bee ignorant of any thing touching their ſaluation, they will certifie vs thereof.</p>
               <p>One of the foure Beaſts had the face of a Man, this ſeemeth to bee Saint <hi>Mathew,</hi> becauſe the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and face of his Goſpell decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the generation of the huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:25079:18"/>of Chriſt from <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Beaſt like the Eagle, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> becauſe he mounts like an Eagle into Heauen, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Diuinity of Chriſt; the other two are <hi>Marke</hi> and <hi>Luke,</hi> one like a Lyon, becauſe hee ſpeakes more largely of the reſurrection of Chriſt, wherein he roſe like a Lion from death, and conquered ſinne, death, and hell: the other was like a Calfe, becauſe hee ſpake more largely of the offering of Chriſt, vpon the Croſſe, which was prefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured by the ſacrifice of Calues in the old Law.</p>
               <p>Their ſixe wings a peece, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſpeedy flying of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell about the world.</p>
               <p>In that they are full of eyes, it ſheweth that by the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wee may ſee Chriſt more plainely then by the old, there we ſee but the types of him, heere wee ſee Chriſt himſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:25079:18"/>
               <p>In that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw thouſand thouſands of Angells, it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what an innumerable num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber there be; the office of theſe bee to preſerue the faithfull in this world, what need we then to feare?</p>
               <p>The Angell interprets the waters where the Whore ſitteth, <hi>Reu.</hi> 17.14. to bee people, ſo this glaſſie Sea before the throne ſignifies the ſoules of the faithfull; ſo it doth in the beginning of the 14. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: The faithfull of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are called <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. ſo great a Cloud of witneſſes, ſignifying, that there was as many of them, as droppes of raine in a great cloud; ſo the ſoules in Heauen are called a Sea, to ſignifie vnto vs that there bee ſuch a number as droppes of water in a Sea, according to Gods promiſe vnto Abraham, that his ſeed, that is, the faithfull, ſhould be ſo many in number, as the ſands on
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:25079:19"/>the Sea ſhore, or the ſtarres in the Element.</p>
               <p>In that it is a glaſſie Sea, though heere afflictions may toſſe our mindes as the windes the waues, yet as no winde can ſtirre a glaſſie Sea, ſo all ſorrow is parted from them, nothing can diſturbe their mindes but they alwayes reioyce in the Lord.</p>
               <p>In that this Sea is of glaſſe an intire ſubſtance, it ſheweth how the ſoules in Heauen be vnited to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in loue, reioyſing euery one at anothers ſaluation as at their owne.</p>
               <p>In that the Sea is like Chriſtall, it ſheweth how holy they are, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer offending their louing God, but are all crowned with Crownes of righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>In that the Angells and they did eſpecially reioyce, when Chriſt obtained to open the ſeales, to ſhew vs this Reuelation, it decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:25079:19"/>how dearly they loue the elect vpon earth, and how profitable this Reuelation is to vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <p>IN that one of the foure Beaſts calleth Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> vnto the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of euery ſeale to ſee what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and his voyce was as thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, it ſheweth that the way to come to Chriſt, and to obtaine any thing at his hand, is to hearken vnto the Goſpell, and that it is as forcible to the heart, as thunder to the eares.</p>
               <p>The white Horſe ſignifieth the Apoſtles &amp; Preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell anone vpon the ſending of the holy Ghoſt, the Rider is Chriſt, his bow whereby hee conquers, the preaching of the Goſpell, his Crowne ſheweth that the Goſpell ſo preuailed, that it got him a Kingdome.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:25079:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:25079:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25079:21"/>
               <p>In that the Apoſtles are called Horſes, it ſheweth their ſwiftneſſe in publiſhing the Goſpell: that white Horſe Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> what a number of Countries did he plant the Goſpell in! <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia and <hi>Philip</hi> brought the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell into England, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the tenth to the Romanes affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that then the ſound of the Goſpell had gone through all the earth, and into the ends of the World.</p>
               <p>The red Horſe ſignifies the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Emperours of Rome, which raiſed the tenne perſecutions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians, the rider was the Diuell, prouoking them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, for he had permiſſion of God, to take peace from the earth, and to kill with the ſword, and he had a great ſword giuen him, which ſheweth that the Diuell doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing vnto Gods children, but by Gods permiſſion, the cauſes why
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:25079:21"/>God will ſuffer the Diuell to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute his children, are beſt knowne vnto his wiſdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nero Domitius</hi> cauſed the firſt Perſecution: He regarded neither ſexe, condition, or age, the ſtreets were ſpred with dead bodies of Chriſtians, he indeuored vtterly to aboliſh the name of Chriſtians, and his Succeſſors followed his ſteppes: for their ſpeed in perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting they may well bee compared to Horſes.</p>
               <p>The blacke Horſe are ſuch as went about to darken the light of the Goſpell, and to maintaine the blackneſſe of Idolatry; the Diuell the Prince of darkeneſſe was their Rider, becauſe he prouoked them therevnto: but he had no power to hurt the oyle and the wine, that is, thoſe that had the oyle of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and the wine of Chriſts blood by a liuely faith.</p>
               <p>The pale Horſe ſeemeth to bee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:25079:22"/>
                  <hi>Diocleſian</hi> which moued the tenth Perſecution, hee is called Death, becauſe hee martyred ſo many Chriſtians in all Countries, at one time hee ſlew 6660. of his owne ſoldiers, becauſe they were Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, hee deſtroyed all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in England: no tongue can vtter the deaths and torments that this Tyrant vſed, hanging them by one hand, ſcourging them, and broyling them not to death, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day: <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith hee ſaw the ſwordes of the Perſecutors blunt with often ſlaughter, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for wearineſſe to ſit downe and reſt, but the Martyrs nothing diſmaid were patient for Chriſts ſake: ſo he did likewiſe in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. Then the ſoules of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that were ſlaine in theſe tenne Perſecutions being vnder the altar which is Chriſt, cryed to God as <hi>Abels</hi> blood did for vengeance, and they had long white robes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:25079:22"/>which is the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, and they were bid to reſt vntill their fellow-ſeruants ſhould be killed as they were, that is, vntill Antichriſt ſhould be more drunken with the bloud of Saints then the Emperours were. But their cries moued the Lord to vengeance, and hee deſtroyed theſe idolatrous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors by the hand of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> whom the Lord made a moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour.</p>
               <p>The Earthquake, the blackneſſe of the Sun, and rednes of the Moon, the falling of the Stars, the vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of heauen, the remouing of the mountaines, and the feare of the great ones, deſiring the mountains and rockes to couer them from the wrath of God, deſcribeth the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of Gods wrath executed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe perſecuting Idolaters: &amp; although theſe things ſhall not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come to paſſe vntil the comming of Chriſt, yet theſe words were vſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:25079:23"/>by Chriſt in propheſying the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Ieruſalem, and in other places of Scripture, when the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of ſome great Iudgement is propheſied.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <p>THe foure Angels that held the foure windes from blowing vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, ſea, or any tree, ſhewes the peace that God had giuen vnto the Church by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> &amp; how God by his Angels preſerued them from perſecutions, ſignified by the windes.</p>
               <p>The ſealing of the 12000. of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tribe, a certaine number for an innumerable number, and a greater number of other Nations, ſheweth the flowriſhing of the Goſpell at that time.</p>
               <p>This likewiſe is declared by the wonderful reioycing of the Angels and Saints in heauen, aſcribing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:25079:23"/>God praiſe, honour glory, &amp; wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thankes. What haue the Martyrs loſt by theſe perſecutions? Though they ſuffered tribulations for a ſmall time, now they are in long white garments, which ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth Chriſts righteouſneſſe, being in the preſence of the throne of God, and ſerue him day and night in his Temple; and hee that ſitteth on the throne will euer dwell with them, and they ſhall haue no more hunger nor thirſt, nor be hurt, but God will gouerne them and leade them to the liuely fountaines of waters, and wipe away all teares from their eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8.</head>
               <p>IN that this peace is ſaid to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue but halfe an houre, it ſhewes that it did not indure long: for the Church beganne to waxe wanton with this great peace, &amp; indeuored
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:25079:24"/>more to get large reuennues and riches of the world, then to ſet forth the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>In their eſtabliſhing Chriſtianity in Rome, to pleaſe the moſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious and idolatrous Romanes, they tranſlated all their Heathen gods of Rome to bee their gods, only by giuing them other names; <hi>Pantheon</hi> which was the houſe of all gods, is <hi>Maria rotunda,</hi> the houſe of all Saints: the place of <hi>Cibel</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of gods, is now placed to <hi>Mary</hi> the mother of God: the temple that was dedicated vnto <hi>Pallas</hi> and <hi>Minerua</hi> is now dedicated vnto <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerua</hi> a virgin; and they inclined to many other pernicious and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſuperſtitions both of the Iewes and Gentiles: Therefore Chriſt is ſiguratiuely ſaid to ſtand before the Altar, with a golden Cenſor, and much odors was giuen him to offer, which was the prayers of Saints; and the ſmoake of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:25079:24"/>which is the prayers of Saints, went vp to God out of Chriſts hand, and hee tooke the denſor and filled it with coales from the Altar, and caſt it into the earth, and there was voyces &amp; thunders, lightnings and earthquakes, all which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Gods moſt heauy indignation againſt them.</p>
               <p>And there was hayle &amp; ſire min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with bloud caſt vpon the earth, and burned the third part of Trees and greene graſſe. The earth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the great men, as the earth is higher then the ſea and flouds; theſe were firſt perſwaded to ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the haile ſignifieth their coldnes in true Religion, the fire mingled with bloud their heat to maintaine ſuperſtitions, euen to the ſhedding of the bloud of ſuch as would not conſent to their ſuperſtitions.</p>
               <p>The great Mountaine that was caſt into the ſea burning with fire, was the Emperour, which by the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:25079:25"/>perſwaſion of the ſuperſtitious, caſt himſelfe from God and Chriſt, and tooke their part to maintaine their ſuperſtitions, and with a burning zeale perſecuted the third part of common people, which are ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the ſea.</p>
               <p>As the Starres ſignified the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the ſeuen Churches, ſo this great Star that fell from heauen is the Biſhop of Rome: by falling from heauen is meant from the Church. This ſeemes to be about the yere 666. according to <hi>Chap.</hi> 13. His bitterneſſe called wormwood, are his wicked Canons and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions: for in that yeare <hi>Vitillianus</hi> Pope ſent into England, and into other Countries, to ſet vp Latine Seruice and Maſſes, Ceremonies, Letanies, and other Romiſh ware. This Star fell into and made bitter the fountains and ſprings, theſe are the Clergy, for they ſhould mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to all men the water of life, as
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:25079:25"/>riuers feede both ſea and land: ſo likewiſe in that he darkned the Sun, Moone and Starres, and the day, this meaneth the Miniſters likewiſe, which ought to make ſhine the bright beames of the Goſpell vnto great and ſmall, and make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues and others Children of the day; the meaning is, that the Biſhop of Rome ſilenced the Biſhops &amp; Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers which were within his Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction from preaching the truth, &amp; made them preach ſuperſtitions and bitter doctrine, to the poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their ſoules. In that there is mention made in all theſe iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments but of the third part of men, it is becauſe there was neuer but the third part of the world that would conſent vnto the Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, ſuperſtitions, and falſe doctrine of the Pope.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:25079:26"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <p>IN this Chapter is a Propheſie of another Star, which S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith was fallen from heauen, becauſe the Popedome was fallen before. This ſeemes to be <hi>Hilaebrand</hi> the Pope, which ioyned vnto the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome the temporall Sword, that is, iutiſdiction ouer all Emperours &amp; Kings, to place them and diſplace them at his pleaſure. Which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in that hee gaue ſuch power to his Locuſts, as hereafter is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: he is ſaid to haue the key of the bottomleſſe pit, which ſheweth that as the Angell in the 20. Chap. had the key of the bottomleſſe pit to binde Sathan, and to ſhut him therein for 1000. yeares, ſo when the 1000. yeares were expired, the Pope had the key of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe pit to let him out againe. The ſmoake that came out of this pit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:25079:26"/>when it was opened, and darkned the Sunne, was their ſuperſtitions and falſe doctrines, that darkned the Goſpel as ſmoake darkens the Sun. The Locuſts that came out, were the Cardinals and Biſhops. Theſe farre differed from the Biſhops of the primitiue Church: they were the onely planters and maintainers of true Religion, theſe the onely confounders &amp; deſtroyers therof.</p>
               <p>The Locuſts in Egypt neuer more deuoured the fruits of the land, then theſe Locuſts did the riches of all Countries, both of their ſoules and of their bodies. Their crownes ſhew the power that they had: their faces like men ſheweth their hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall and fayre ſpeeches: their hayre like women declareth their flattering allurements that they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: their Lions tee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h their cruelty, and what deuourers of men they were: their iron haubergions ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the temporall iuriſdiction that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:25079:27"/>they had: their wings, and chariots with many horſes, ſheweth their ſwiftneſſe and power to doe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe: their tayles like Scorpions, with heads and crownes on them, and ſtings, were their Subſtitutes and Officers, to whom they gaue great power, as appeareth by their heads and crownes; Theſe ſo much ſtung and vexed the people, that they were weary of their liues.</p>
               <p>In that theſe had not power to hurt thoſe that were marked by the Angell for God in the fore-heads, it ſheweth, that yet the diuels time was not come, to bee let looſe to ſhed the bloud of Saints; and it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth the prouidence of God vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the faithfull, and that hee had euer his Church in the moſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous times.</p>
               <p>In that theſe Locuſts came out of the bottomleſſe pit, it ſheweth that they were of the diuell, and if the Diuell himſelfe had beene in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:25079:27"/>the ſhape of man, he could not be worſe then they were.</p>
               <p>In that they had power to hurt but for fiue moneths, it is common with the holy Ghoſt in propheſies, to ſet a day for a yeare, and at 30. dayes to the moneth, which was the Iewes computation, fiue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths is 150. dayes, which ſheweth that their chiefe regalitie and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er was to continue but 150. yeares.</p>
               <p>In that this Starre is ſaid to haue the key of the bottomleſſe pit, wee may ſee how much the Pope decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs, in vaunting that hee hath the keyes of heauen, when they are but the keyes of hell.</p>
               <p>The mighty power of the Pope at this time, is declared, in that that hee is called the King ouer the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts: and in that he could conferre ſuch great power vpon them: and in that hee is ſaid to be the Angell of the bottomleſſe pit, it ſheweth, that hee had all the power that the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:25079:28"/>diuell could doe to ſtrengthen him, and it appeares what a deſtroyer the Pope is, in that the holy Ghoſt nameth him Deſtruction.</p>
               <p>This Viſion following in the 14. Verſe of this Chapter, and the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the 7. Verſe of the 20. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are all one: Now the 1000. yeares that the diuell ſhould bee bound, being expired, the Goſpell beginning to reuiue again, he hath liberty to rage and ſtirre againe, that the might of Chriſt might bee ſeene in defending his ſilly Lambes againſt the diuell the roaring Lion, and all the popiſh Wolues though they were neuer ſo ſtrong.</p>
               <p>The infinite number of warriers that <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaw and told, were the very ſame Locuſts before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: for the deſcription of theſe &amp; them are all one in all points, and their battell was againſt the Saints, as appeareth in the 20. Chapter.</p>
               <p>The fire, ſmoake, and brimſtone,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:25079:28"/>that went out of their mouthes, were their Excommunications, in that like ſmoake they breathed out, that whoſoeuer diſobeyed them ſhould be eternally burnt in Hell with fire and brimſtone.</p>
               <p>In that the Diuell is ſaid to be foure Angels, it is becauſe as ſoone as he was ſet at liberty, as is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the 20. Chapter, he went in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the foure quarters of the earth, to prouoke men againſt the Children of God: in that hee got ſuch an infinite number, theſe were the Pope, Cardinals, Biſhops, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bots, Fryers, and their officers, to martyr the Saints.</p>
               <p>In that it is ſaid hee came from the riuer Euphrates, it was to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, that as the Babilonians came from Euphrates to deſtroy the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Temple, ſo ſhould this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Babilon deſtroy the ſpirituall Temple.</p>
               <p>If wee conſider the martyrdome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:25079:29"/>of the Waldences in France, and their maſſacres, and the Martyres that their Inquiſitions haue deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there, and all that haue beene martyred in England fince <hi>Wicklifs</hi> time, &amp; thoſe that haue beene mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred in Bohemia, Germany, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and by their Inquiſitions in Spaine &amp; other places, we ſhall ſee that the Diuell by theſe Locuſts ſince his letting looſe hath ſlaine more of Gods children, then euer he did before he was bound.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding the mighty hoaſt of the diuell, and all his Popiſh train, yet we ſee how Chriſt hath preuailed. As <hi>Sauls</hi> kingdome decreaſed and <hi>Dauids</hi> increaſed, ſo the Lord be prayſed, wee daily ſee Chriſts kingdome increaſe, &amp; the Popes more and more ruinated: let the Ieſuites the Angels of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:25079:29"/>pit, deuiſe neuer ſo many diuelliſh practiſes to vphold the ſame, the viſion of Chriſt in this Chapter declareth ſo much.</p>
               <p>His Rainebow about his head, teacheth vs, that the Diuell by the Pope and his Locuſts ſhall preuaile no more ouer vs, euen as the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow aſſureth vs the world ſhall bee no more drowned.</p>
               <p>His face ſhineth, to ſhew his fauor to ſuch as haue forſaken all Popiſh errors and truſt in him onely: &amp; his braſen feet certifieth vs, that he will tread the Diuell, the Pope, and all his Locuſts vnder his feete.</p>
               <p>In that he ſets one foot on the ſea, and the other foot on the land, it may hence infallibly be gathered, that after Chriſt ſhall deſtroy the Popedome, the very Turkes and Iewes, and all Papiſts that remaine, ſhall bee conuerted to beleeue in Chriſt onely, and his elect among them ſhall be ſaued.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:25079:30"/>
               <p>In that Chriſt ſweares that there ſhall be no more time, but in the dayes of the voyce of the ſeauenth Angell, when hee ſhall blow the Trumpet, the myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed, it may be moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded, that not long after the deſtruction of the Popedome Chriſt ſhall come to Iudgement.</p>
               <p>In that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> is forbidden to to write the voyce of the feauen thunders, we muſt learne that there be ſome things that the Lord will not haue reuealed vnto vs, as is the day of Chriſts comming to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the certaine day of the deſtruction of Antichriſt, and ſuch like: and that whatſoeuer is written by his commandement, we may be bold and ought to begge of Chriſt by prayer, and by all meanes ſeeke for the vnderſtanding thereof.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> his eating of the booke was his certaine vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the things contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:25079:30"/>and the knowledge thereof was ſweet to him at the firſt, but when hee had well conſidered how the Diuell ſhould haue ſuch great power to perſecure the Saints, and to ſpill their blood in ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant manner, the knowledge heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was moſt bitter vnto him, then S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> is commanded of Chriſt to propheſie againe amongſt the people, Nations and Tongues, and to many Kings, according to which in the next Chapter, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> beginneth a new Reuelation of all things that hath beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed touching Antichriſt, in a more large and ample manner, then in this Reuelation already is declared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 11.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOſeph</hi> telleth <hi>Pharoah Gen.</hi> 41 32. therefore the Dreame was do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled vnto <hi>Pharoah</hi> the ſecond time,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:25079:31"/>becauſe the thing is eſtabliſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God: euen ſo, becauſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies in this Reuelation are eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and ſure to be performed: and to make them the more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely and manifeſtly of vs to bee vnderſtood &amp; beleeued, all things that haue beene reuealed touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Antichriſt, are from this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto the end of the Booke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed againe, but farre more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and plainely delared then in the former: but in this is nothing prophiſied but the things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>In the 8. Chapter Chriſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the prayers of the faithfull to God, and then filleth the Cenſor with coales of the Altar, and threw them vpon the earth, and there fell vpon the earth hayle, and fire min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with blood, and it burnt the third part of Trees and greene graſſe.</p>
               <p>Wherein I ſhewed the great
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:25079:31"/>peace the Church enioyed by <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> in which proſperity the Romiſh Church fell to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions and anger'd God: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee gaue them ouer to their owne luſtes, vntill the Romane Church became the Synagogue of Sathan and Antichriſt, and they became as colde as hayle in true religion and as hot as fire euen to the ſhedding of blood, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their ſuperſtitions.</p>
               <p>In this Chapter they that truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed only vnto the blood of Chriſt, by an alluſion vnto the temple of <hi>Salomon,</hi> are ſaid to be the temple of God, and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to meaſure them to God: and the ſuperſtitious Romanes, and thoſe that tooke their parts are ſaid to be the Courts, becauſe they make a ſhew of Religion, but with ſuperſtitions prophane the truth, therefore Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to caſt them out, and not to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:25079:32"/>mete them; and theſe ſhall tread the holy Citty, that is, the Children of God, vnder their feete 42. moneths, this time is likewiſe ſet forth in this Chapter to bee 1260. dayes, and alſo 3. dayes and a halfe, theſe times are all one, the three dayes and a halfe, ſignifie three yeares and a halfe, and in three yeares and a halfe there is iuſt 42. moneths, and in ſo many moneths, at 30. dayes to the Moneth, which was the Iewes Computation, there is 1260. dayes, and it is common with the Holy ghoſt in Propheſies to ſet downe a day for a yeare, ſo Antichriſt muſt raigne 1260. yeares.</p>
               <p>The two witneſſes are the olde and new Teſtaments, and all that preach and teach them all the time of Antichriſt, theſe ſhall bee two oliue trees ſpiritually to feede the ſoules of the Elect, and to conuey the oyle of the holy Ghoſt into
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:25079:32"/>them, and they ſhall be two lamps to lighten them in the wayes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and they ſhall ſtand before the Pope the God of the earth, and if any hurt the Preachers of them, the Lord will ſend plagues from heauen vpon ſuch.</p>
               <p>In that they are ſaid to be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in Sackcloth, it ſheweth, that the Profeſſors of them ſhall be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing regarded, and ſhall haue all this time great cauſe to mourne for the little regard that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell had, and for the ſuperſtitions and ſinnes of the people.</p>
               <p>In the ſeauenth verſe, when they haue finiſhed their teſtimony, the Beaſt out of the bottomleſſe pit ſhall make warre againſt them, and ouercome them, and kill them; this is after the looſing of Sathan.</p>
               <p>Their corpes ſhall be dead and vnburied in Rome; that is, as a dead carcaſſe long vnburied, is noyſome to bee ſeene or ſmelt,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:25079:33"/>euen ſo noyſome was the word of God, and the preaching thereof vnto them all the time of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, yet they could not bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their corpes all this while, that is, they could not quite pur downe the preaching of the word; but the Lord ſtill ſtirred vp ſome, (yea though they dyed for it) to tell them of their idolatries, ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, murther, ſorcery, fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and theft.</p>
               <p>It ſheweth what great power the Diuel hath ouer the vnregenerate, that hee can make them reioyce, and bring gifts one to another, for ioy that the preaching of the word is ſuppreſt, and the bookes of the word it ſelfe, as the Papiſts haue done theſe many ages, reioycing that their meanes of Saluation is taken from them, and that they are not hindred from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing headlong vnto eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:25079:33"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rome</hi> is called ſpiritually <hi>Zodome,</hi> becauſe they exceed <hi>Zodome</hi> in the ſinnes therof; and it is called <hi>Egypt,</hi> becauſe they haue oppreſſed the Children of God more then the Egyptians did the Iſraelites, and Chriſt was ſlaine in <hi>Rome,</hi> in that <hi>Pilate</hi> a Romane Iudge condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, and the Romane officers crucified him.</p>
               <p>That after the 1260. yeares God ſent the ſpirit into the two witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wee ſee the truth of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie performed, and we ſee them ſtand vpon their feet, and the feare of them is vpon the Pope, and all his Clergie, and God hath taken them vp into Heauen, and exalted and preſerued them in the ſight of their enemies and the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by them hath beene ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as with a mighty Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, that the tenth part haue become Proteſtants long agoe, and dayly his Kingdome hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:25079:34"/>and the Proteſtants increaſed.</p>
               <p>In that it is ſaid that 7000. were killed with this earthquake, and the reſt glorified God, it ſheweth that when Rome ſhall bee deſtroyed all the Papiſts (that then remaine ſhall become Proteſtants.</p>
               <p>When the ſeauenth Angell ſhall blow his trumpet, the Pope ſhall bee quite deſtroyed, and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the world ſhall bee our Lord Chriſts, and hee ſhall raigne for euermore; and all in Heauen ſhal reioyce and ſay, We giue thee thanks Lord God Almighty, for thou haſt receiued thy great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and obtained thy Kingdome; the Gentiles were angry, and thy wrath is come, and the time that the dead ſhall bee iudged, and that thou ſhouldeſt giue reward vnto thy Prophets and Saints and them that feare thy name, and that thou ſhouldeſt deſtroy them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the earth.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:25079:34"/>
               <p>In that it is ſaid, then the temple of God was open, and the Arke of the Couenant was ſeene, and that there were lightenings and voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thunder and great hayle; it ſheweth Gods anger againſt the diſobedient to his word, that then there ſhall bee no interruption of the preaching thereof, and that the Lord will hinder and puniſh ſuch as offer to hinder, and will not obey it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 12.</head>
               <p>AS in the eighth Chapter, is a viſion of a great Mountaine that fell burning into the Sea, which there is interpreted to bee the Emperour, taking the part of the ſuperſtitious Romanes, againſt the faithfull in Chriſt: Heere the Emperour is called, a great red Dragon which ſheweth the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his perſecution againſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:25079:35"/>Gods Children for reſiſting ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions.</p>
               <p>The woman that was cloathed with the Sunne, and the Moone vnder her feet, and vpon her head a Crowne of twelue ſtarres, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the flouriſhing eſtate of the Church by <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell ſhined from them as the Sun and Moone, and the teſtimony of the twelue Apoſtles was their Crowne and reioycing, and as twelue ſtarres to direct them: her trauelling with child, was the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of the faithfull, which the Dragon, the Emperour, ſought by all meanes to deuoure: they are called a Man child, becauſe Chriſt the Man-child and they are but all one; their taking vp into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſheweth their preſeruation of God.</p>
               <p>In that it is ſaide, they ſhall rule the Nations with a rodde of Iron, it is, becauſe Chriſt their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:25079:35"/>head ſhall doe ſo for them.</p>
               <p>The Dragons Taile that drew the third part of the ſtarres of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and caſt them to the earth, his taile ſignifieth his edicts, and the executioners therof; the ſtarres are the faithfull Children of God, which ſhine like ſtarres in reſpect of Infidells: the third part ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the Popes iuriſdiction, for he neuer had dominion but in the third part of the World, and the Heauen heere is the Church: I leaue the interpretation of his 7. heads and ten hornes vnto the 17. Chapter, where the Angell inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets them.</p>
               <p>The flying of the woman into the wildernes, ſheweth what feare the faithfull were put in, that they were faine to haue priuate mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, as if it were in a wildernes; and this continued, 1260. yeares: concerning the battell in Heauen, <hi>Michael</hi> and his Angells are Chriſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:25079:36"/>and his Preachers, againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell and Papiſts his Soldiers; and Chriſt and his Children gatte the victory in the end; and Chriſt and his ſhall raigne in inſpeakeable glory, when as the Diuell and all that tooke his part in reſiſting the Goſpell, ſhall inherit eternall paine and torments.</p>
               <p>When this victory was, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> heard a loud voyce, ſaying, Now is Saluation in Heauen, that is, the Church, and ſtrength, and the Kingdome of our God, and the power of Chriſt, for the accuſer of our brethren is caſt downe: there was neuer any that ſo falſly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the faithfull, as the Papiſts haue, and ſtill doe, like vnto the Diuell their Captaine, which accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs day and night before God; but they ouercame him by the bloud of the Lambe, and the word of their teſtimony, and they loued not their liues vnto death; this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:25079:36"/>certifieth vs who were Chriſts An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells that fought againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.</p>
               <p>Reioyce yee Heauens and they that dwell therein, meaning the faithfull in the true Church: woe to the Inhabitants of the earth and and ſea: The earth is often in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted great men, and the ſea the common people; meaning carnall men, for the Diuell is come downe vnto you hauing great wrath, knowing he hath but a ſhort time; this is, ſince the 1000. yeares that the Diuell is let looſe.</p>
               <p>When the Dragon ſaw that hee was caſt into the earth, that is, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, hee perſecuted the woman, but God preſerued her as an Eagle ſaueth her ſelfe with flying aloft, and as one that ſaueth himſelfe by hiding in the wildernes; and the Dragon caſt out water after the woman, like a flood, that he might
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:25079:37"/>carry her away, but the earth hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the woman, that is, God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided men of the earth euer all this 1260. yeares to defend and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour his children: by the Dragon is meant, not only the Emperours, but the Popes; for ſince the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors power decaid, the Popes were as Emperours.</p>
               <p>Then the Dragon made warre with the ſeed of the woman, which keepe the Commandements of God, and haue the teſtimony of Ieſus Chriſt, theſe are the warres that long haue beene, and now are betwixt the Papiſts and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 13.</head>
               <p>THe two Beaſts in the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of this Chapter, are the two ſtarres that the Propheſies are of in the 8. and 9. Chapters, and both ſet out vnto vs the Popes.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:25079:37"/>
               <p>The firſt Beaſt is ſaid to ariſe out of the Sea, that is, from amongſt the lower ſort of men; which is, when <hi>Phocas</hi> had ſlaine his Maiſter <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Emperour &amp; all his Children, and made himſelfe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, he gaue <hi>Boniface</hi> Biſhop of Rome preheminence to be higheſt aboue all other Biſhops, and ſole ruler of them.</p>
               <p>In that he is ſaid to haue ſeauen heads, and tenne hornes, with Crownes vpon them, the reaſon is ſet downe in the ſecond verſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Dragon gaue him his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and his throne, and his great power, to enable him to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Children of God.</p>
               <p>In that there was ſet vpon his head the name of blaſphemie, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Pope taketh to himſelfe that which onely belongeth to Chriſt, to haue all power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and Earth, and whatſoeuer prerogatiue the Scripture attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:25079:38"/>to Chriſt, the Pope moſt blaſphemouſly taketh to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>In that he is like the Leopard, no Beaſt is ſo beautifully ſpotted as the Leopard is; ſo no Emperour or King was euer ſo richly or glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly decked with gold and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones, as the Popes haue beene.</p>
               <p>In that his clawes are like the clawes of a Beare, which hath the ſtrongeſt pawes of all Beaſts to catch and to hold withall; it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that neuer any Emperour, or any elſe, hath been ſuch an exactor of the riches of all Lands, as the Popes haue beene, as Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Hiſtories make mention.</p>
               <p>In that his mouth was as the mouth of a Lyon, it ſheweth his tyranny, cruelty, and mercileſnes, in deuouring Gods children, and well may the holy Ghoſt ſtile him a Beaſt that hath theſe beaſtly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: his head that was wounded
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:25079:38"/>to death was the Emperour, when <hi>Mauritius</hi> and his Children were ſlaine: But <hi>Hiraclius</hi> the Emperour killed <hi>Phocas</hi> that ſlew them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored the Empire againe.</p>
               <p>And the ſuperſtitious gloried in the Pope being made ſo great by the Emperour, and worſhipped the Dragon that gaue power vnto him; and they worſhipped the Beaſt, ſaying, Who is like vnto the Beaſt? Who is able to warre with him? And the Beaſt blaſphemed God, and his name, and his taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and them that dwell in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, that is, his faithfull Children: and hee warred againſt the Saints and ouercame them, and power was giuen him ouer euery King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and tongue, and Nation; therefore all that are in the earth ſhall worſhip him, whoſe names are not written in the Booke of life. But heere is the benefit of the patience and faith of Saints; if any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:25079:39"/>lead into Captiuity, he ſhall be led into Captiuity, and whoſoeuer killed them by the ſword, ſhall bee killed by the ſword.</p>
               <p>This ſecond Beaſt, is the ſecond ſtarre in the ninth Chapter, which is <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> which ioyned the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, vnto the Popedome, that is, temporall iuriſdiction ouer the Emperour and the ten Kings, to place them and diſplace them at his pleaſure, which is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that hee is ſaid to haue two hornes like the Lambe Chriſt, that is, to bee King of Kings and Lord of Lords, as well as Ruler ouer ſoules.</p>
               <p>Whereas his Predeceſſors had the Emperours power and iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction but by permiſſion and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, hee and his Succeſſors clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the ſupremacie of duty giuen vnto them of God, alleadging all thoſe places of Scriptures, which declareth what ſupremacie God
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:25079:39"/>hath giuen vnto Chriſt ouer all in heauen and earth, for his proofes thereof, and ſo made the image of the firſt Beaſt, that is, like as the firſt beaſt had the power of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, but in fauour; hee annexed the power and ſupremacie aboue all Emperours and Kings, as an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent and duty vnto the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome for euer, and he ſpake as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuouſly as the Dragon, &amp; did execute his power in the Emperors ſight, that is, as not hauing his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer from him but from God.</p>
               <p>This Beaſt did great ſignes, ſo that hee made fire to deſcend vpon earth in the ſight of men, but theſe ſignes were done by Nigromancy, wherefore after Pope <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned by a general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and for coniuration and dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the Diuell, &amp; many other grieuous offences, hee was by the ſaid Councell depriued from being Pope: but his Succeſſors vnto this
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:25079:40"/>day ſtill maintaine the doctrine of his vſurped Supremacie ouer all Princes. And this Beaſt made a law that whoſoeuer would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt ſhould bee ſlaine.</p>
               <p>The number of the beaſts name is 666. this is to ſhew, that at that time the firſt beaſt beganne to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the Church with ſuperſtitions and falſe doctrines, as is declared in Chap. 8. of the firſt Starre.</p>
               <p>In that in the fift verſe of this Chapter, there is a mouth giuen vnto the beaſt to ſpeak blaſphemies 42. moneths, which is interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Chap. 11. to be 1260. yeares, ſo that iuſt this time was appointed vnto the People, Emperour, and Pope, and it ſheweth, that they all this time ioyned together, to tread downe the holy Citie, the true Church, all this while.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:25079:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. 14.</head>
               <p>NOw Antichriſt is reuealed in ſuch liuely colours, that none except the diuell blinde his eyes, but may ſee the Pope to bee Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: now in this Chapter begins to be declared his deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Chriſts ſtanding vpon mount Sion, ſignifieth his preſence with his children: the 144000. that were with him, which were ſealed in the 7. Chapter, a certaine number for an innumerable number, declaring that all the Saints who all this time of 1260. yeares were martyred or perſecuted by Antichriſt, were with him in glory, and none of them loſt.</p>
               <p>In that the ſound of their voices was like the roaring of many wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and like thunder, it declareth, what a multitude of them there be.</p>
               <p>In that they played vpon harps, and ſung a new ſong which none
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:25079:41"/>could learne but themſelues, their harping ſheweth how ioyfully they praiſed God, &amp; that none can ſing ſuch new ſongs, and ſo much praiſe God, as thoſe which haue ſuffered for ſtanding faithfully in the truth, and haue beene deliuered.</p>
               <p>In that they are commended for not being defiled with women, it is not onely meant of their bodily chaſtity, but alſo of their ſpirituall chaſtitie, in that Antichriſt had not made them commit ſpirituall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication by following his idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous doctrines: but they were vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, that did onely cleaue vnto their Spouſe Chriſt and his word. In their mouthes was found no guile, they taught onely the truth, they were without ſpot before the throne of God, that is, in the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now the 1260. yeares of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt appeare plainely to bee fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, in that the Goſpell doth ſo
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:25079:41"/>plentifully flouriſh: and in that wee ſee Chriſt vpon mount Sion, that is, defending his Church. And here wee haue a promiſe that this ſhall be an euerlaſting Goſpell, that is, to indure vnto Chriſts comming, as which ſo great a grace was neuer ſhewed vnto former ages; therfore the Angell that brings vs theſe glad tidings, exhorts vs, to feare God &amp; giue glory vnto him, for the houre of his iudgement is come; and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him that made heauen and earth, and the fountaines of water.</p>
               <p>Then is propheſied that Rome ſhall bee deſtroyed, called by the name of great Babylon; becauſe as the Babylonians deſtroyed the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall Temple, ſo haue they of Rome the ſpirituall Temple, the faithfull: the cauſe of her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on followeth, Becauſe ſhee hath made drunken all nations with the wine of the wrath of her fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that is, of her idolatrous and falſe doctrine.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:25079:42"/>
               <p>Therefore there followes a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that whoſoeuer ſhall worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, that is, the Pope, and receiue the print of his name, that is, make holineſſe in croſſing himſelfe, and in other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions, hee ſhall drinke of the wine of the wrath of God, and bee tormented in fire and brimſtone before the holy Angels and before the Lambe, and the ſmoake of their torments ſhall aſcend euermore, and they ſhall haue no reſt day nor night.</p>
               <p>In that the deſtruction of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt followeth the preaching of the Goſpell, it declareth, that by it Antichriſt ſhall bee deſtroyed, and that the ſuppreſſion of the preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word was the cauſe of the growth of it: and therefore it is, that the diuell puts into the heads of Papiſts, to keepe all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the reading, hearing, and preaching of Gods word.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:25079:42"/>
               <p>The voyce from heauen that bad <hi>Iohn</hi> write, Bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours, and their workes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, ought to incourage vs to preach the Goſpell, to the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe of Antichriſt, though we ſuffer neuer ſo much for our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>After the fall of Antichriſt by the preaching of the Goſpell, and that the Lord hath fulfilled the number of the elect, then ſhall Chriſt come vpon a white cloud wearing a golden crowne, &amp; in his hand a ſickle, and becauſe the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt of the earth is ripe, heeſhall thruſt in his ſickle, and the earth ſhall be reaped, that is, by an alluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to husbandmen in harueſt, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared how Chriſt ſhall gather his Saints to him into heauen.</p>
               <p>And by the Angell that with a ſharp ſickle cut vp the vineyards of the earth, becauſe her grapes were
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:25079:43"/>ripe, and caſt them into the great winepreſſe of the wrath of God, &amp; the winepreſſe was trodden with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Citie, &amp; the bloud, or wine, of the grapes was vnto the horſe bridles by the ſpace of 1600. fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs. By an alluſion to grape-ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers is declared how Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ſhall caſt the reprobate into eternall torments: and in that the winepreſſe is without the Citie, it ſheweth that the place of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhall be ſeparated from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect: and in that there was ſuch plenty of grapes, that the wine or bloud of them was vp to the horſes bridles that trode the preſſes, for the ſpace of 1600. furlongs, it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the multitude of the number of the damned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 15.</head>
               <p>IN this Chapter begins the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the deſtruction of Rome
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:25079:43"/>and the Popedome, by the ſeauen laſt plagues: which viſion S. <hi>Iohn</hi> cals a great and meruailous ſigne. The glaſſie ſea in the 4. Chapter is interpreted the ſoules of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: there it was like Chriſtall: but here like fire, ſhewing that the ſoules of the faithfull burned in zeale for the martyrdomes and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of Antichriſt: and when they ſaw theſe 7. plagues goe forth they reioyced, eſpecially the ſoules of thoſe whom Antichriſt had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred and perſecuted. Their ioy is ſignified by their harps, and they ſung the new ſong of <hi>Moſes</hi> when he was deliuered from <hi>Pharao,</hi> and the ſong of Chriſt when hee was rayſed from death, that is, Great &amp; meruailous are thy workes Lord God Almighty, iuſt and true are thy wayes, King of Saints, who ſhall not feare thee O Lord, and glorifie thy name? for thou onely art holy, and all nations ſhal come and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:25079:44"/>before thee, for thy iudgments are made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>The Tabernacle in heauen that S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw open, is the Church of the faithfull, which by preaching opens a doore for all, by beliefe to enter into the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>In that the 7. Angels with the vials of Gods wrath came out of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, to wit, the Church, it ſheweth, that they were ſent at the prayers of the faithfull: their long white roabes is the righteouſnes of Chriſt: their golden girdles ſignifie the gloriouſneſſe and pureneſſe of their loue to God and his children, for loue is the band of perfection.</p>
               <p>In that the Angels poure out the vials of Gods wrath, it ſhewes that God vſeth them as inſtruments to puniſh the wicked: and though An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt is and ſhall be deſtroyed by men, they are but the inſtrumentall cauſe of God and his Angels.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:25079:44"/>
               <head>CHAP. 16.</head>
               <p>THe firſt, ſecond &amp; third plagues are, that there fell a grieuous and noyſome ſore vpon them who had the mark of the Beaſt and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the image of the Beaſt: in that the ſea and waters became bloud, it ſignifieth that many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be ſlaine. Theſe ſeeme to propheſie the victories that the Turks, &amp; other the Popes enemies, haue had againſt the Papiſts, &amp; the ſlaughters they haue committed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, which was the iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, as appeares <hi>ver.</hi> 5. in that an Angell ſaith, Lord thou art iuſt, becauſe thou haſt iudged theſe things; for they ſhed the bloud of the Saints, &amp; of the Prophets, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haſt thou giuen them bloud to drinke, for they are worthy. And an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Angell ſaid, Euen ſo Lord God Almighty, true and righteous are thy iudgements.</p>
               <p>The fourth plague poured vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:25079:45"/>the Sunne, ſeemes to bee vpon their clergy; this was the ouerthrow of the Cardinals, Biſhops, Abbots, Monks, Friers, Nuns, and all their houſes and dens in England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; other reformed countries: this plague tormented them with heate of fire, and made them boyle in great heate, and blaſpheme the name of God, yet they repented not, to giue God glory.</p>
               <p>The fiſt viall fell vpon the throne of the Pope, &amp; this was the cutting off of his reuennues, which were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite out of all countries, and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was the moſt profitable in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uennues vnto the Pope of all coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and therefore was called the Popes Aſſe, for bearing all taxes &amp; impoſitions that the Popes &amp; Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals laid vpon it; but now the Pope is faine to allow maintenance for vpholding of Popery in al coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: this hath wonderfully darkned the brightnes of his glory and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:25079:45"/>and this makes them gnaw their tongues for ſorrow, and to blaſpheme the God of heauen for their paines and their ſores, and yet they repent not of their works.</p>
               <p>The ſixt plague is the drying vp of the waters of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> that the way of the Kings of the Eaſt ſhould be prepared: this is an allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the deſtruction of the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Babilon; the meaning is, that as the Medes and Perſians, turned the Riuer <hi>Euphrates</hi> out of his courſe, whereby they went ouer &amp; deſtroyed Babilon; ſo the Lord will take away all impediments, that the ten King domes that haue hitherto taken part with the Pope, may deſtroy <hi>Rome</hi> the ſpirituall Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon, as the Angell interpreteth it in the next Chapter.</p>
               <p>The three vncleane ſpirits that came out of the mouth of the Pope, for now the Pope is the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon in that hee is aboue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:25079:46"/>and as mighty and full of venome, and as ready to ſting and poyſon Gods children as any Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon: and he is the Beaſt in reſpect of his beaſtly conditions, and the falſe witneſſe in reſpect of all his falſe doctrines.</p>
               <p>Theſe vncleane ſpirits are the Ieſuites, for they are ſworne at the Popes command to goe into any Countrey and ſpend their liues for the vpholding of the Popedome; theſe are the rotten pillers which proppe vp the falling tower of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell, the Popedome; they are called three, in reſpect of the triple diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Popes Dominions, to wit, into the land, the ſea, &amp; Riuers.</p>
               <p>They are compared to frogges, to ſhew they doe as much hurt all Countries as the frogs did Egipt, and they are as lothſome in the ſight of God and men, as frogs are in our ſights, as frogs turne all things that they eat to poyſon; ſo
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:25079:46"/>doe they all Scriptures to the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning of ſoules, and their ſtudy is nothing but treaſons, poyſonings and murders of proteſtant Kings, Princes, and Countries, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this Propheſie, at the time that God hath appointed, their wicked practiſes ſhall open the eyes of all Kings to ſee the vildnes and horrible wickednes of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and bee prouoked againſt that great day of the Lord to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregate themſelues in <hi>Arma Ged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which may be interpreted, a houſe or temple falling, meaning <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Popedome, being now ready to fall.</p>
               <p>The ſeauenth Angell powreth out his viall into the ayre, that is, ſets the ayre againſt Antichriſt, which is, the breath of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and their preachings vexed and tormented him like thunders and lightenings, and ſhooke the Popedome like the greateſt earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:25079:47"/>that euer was, and made the greateſt part of the Popedome to fall, and become Proteſtants, which the Lord be praiſed for it, wee ſee already to bee performed: and their preaching was like vnto the greateſt hayle that euer was, euery hayleſtone as big and heauy as a talent weight, by which figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue ſpeeches, is ſignified the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deſtruction of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell interpreteth it ſaying, It is done, and in that it is ſaid, The Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Nations fell, and great Babilon came in remembrance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to giue her the cup of the fierceneſſe of his wrath, and that the Iles, that is, them of the Iles, and the mountaines, that is, the great ones, fled away, that is, departed from the Popes falſe doctrines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:25079:47"/>
               <head>CHAP. 17.</head>
               <p>IN this Chapter an Angell ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth St. <hi>Iohn</hi> Rome in a viſion, and interpreteth all the hardeſt things to bee vnderſtood in this Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>He calleth <hi>Rome</hi> the great whore that ſitteth vpon many waters, and ſheweth that all Kings and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the earth are drunken with the wine of her fornication.</p>
               <p>In the viſion, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw a woman ſit vpon a skarlet colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red beaſt full of names of blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, which had ſeauen heads and tenne hornes, and the woman was arrayed in purple and ſcarlet, and guilded with gold, precious ſtones, and pearles, and had a cup of gold in her hand full of abominations and filthines of her fornications, and in her forehead was a myſtery written, Great Babilon the Mother of whoredomes and abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: and the woman was drunken
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:25079:48"/>with the blood of Saints and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Ieſus, and he wondred with great maruell, then the Angell told Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> he would ſhew him the myſtery thereof.</p>
               <p>The Beaſt which thou haſt ſeene was and is not, and ſhall aſcend out of the bottomleſſe pit, and ſhall be deſtroyed, and all that are not written in the booke of life ſhall wonder at it, that hee being ſo mighty could be deſtroyed: this Beaſt is the Emperour, which was before the Reuelation, it ſeemeth at the time thereof the Emperour: was dead and no other then cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and the Pope ſhould aſcend out of the bottomleſſe pitte, and be aboue the Emperour, and for all his greatneſſe yet hee ſhall goe into perdition.</p>
               <p>The Angell declareth the ſeauen heads to ſignifie ſeauen moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines wheron the Whore ſitteth, which plainely ſheweth the Citty
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:25079:48"/>of Rome to bee that Whore, for that is builded vpon ſeauen Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and ſo is no other Citty.</p>
               <p>Againe, the Angell interpreteth the ſeauen heads to bee ſeauen Kings, that is, ſeauen kinds of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment in <hi>Rome,</hi> of which fiue were fallen, and the Idolatrous Emperours did then raigne: but <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſhould quite alter the gouernment of <hi>Rome</hi> from idolatry to Chriſtianity, and hee and the Emperours following him was the ſeauenth King, and the Beaſt in this viſion, which is the Pope, is one of the ſeauenth gouernment in name, becauſe he profeſſeth the name of Chriſt, but indeed he is the eighth gouernment; for hee hath quite changed the gouernment of <hi>Rome,</hi> from Chriſtianity to Popery.</p>
               <p>The Angell interpreteth the ten hornes, to be ten Kings which at the time of the Reuelation had not receiued a kingdome, but ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:25079:49"/>power at one hower with the Pope, and they ſhall be all of one minde and giue their power and authority to him, and fight with Chriſt, but hee ſhall ouercome them. Then the Angell interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the waters where the Whore ſitteth to ſignifie people, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, Nations and tongues; which plainely declareth the Citty of <hi>Rome</hi> to bee the Whore; for no Citty from Chriſt to this day hath ſo many Countries and People vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her dominion, as that Citty: and in the eighth verſe, the Angell interpreteth the woman to be the great Citty, which at the time of the Reuelation raigned ouer the Kings of the earth, and then was the Emperours ſeate there.</p>
               <p>In that the woman ſitteth vpon a ſcarlet coloured Beaſt, it is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ordinary attire of the Pope and Cardinalls is ſcarlet: and his fulneſſe of names of blaſphemy,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:25079:49"/>is, becauſe moſt blaſphemouſly he attributes vnto himſelfe all Chriſts names.</p>
               <p>In that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo richly arrayed in purple, ſcarlet, and guilded with gold and precious ſtones, and pearles; thus were the Popes, Cardinalls, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Prelates, Churches and Idolls arrayed, and doth moſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declare that theſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies are of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The golden Cuppe that ſhe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in her hand, is, her golden name that ſhee ſtileth her ſelfe withall, calling her ſelfe the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, but her doctrines which ſhee teacheth, are filthy and abhominable blaſphemies, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, &amp; ſuperſtitions, which are the wine of her fornication, wherewith ſhee made all Nations of the earth drunken, and ſhee is called the great Whore, in that ſhee is depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſelfe, and hath carried ſo
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:25079:50"/>many from Chriſt our Spowſe, and from his word, and committed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with the Diuell and his wicked doctrines, and for this cauſe it is, that the myſtery, Great Babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, is written in her forehead, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee is the mother of whor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and abominations of the earth, as Babilon was.</p>
               <p>If there were no other note wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it might bee knowne that theſe Prophefies are of <hi>Rome,</hi> this were ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to declare the ſame, in that ſhe is ſaid to be drunken with the blood of Saints and Martyrs of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, for the Romane Gouernours crucified Chriſt, and the Romane Emperours made the tenne perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, and the Romane Popes haue ſlaine more Martyrs &amp; Saints of Ieſus, then euer were ſlaine in the world before.</p>
               <p>The Angell telleth vs in the 16. verſe, that the ten Kings which did with one conſent giue their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:25079:50"/>vnto the Pope, vntill the wordes of God, which hee fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told were fulfilled, are they that ſhall hate the Whore and make her deſolate, and naked, and ſhall eate her fleſh, and burne her with fire, and the performance heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is contained in the two next Chapters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 18.</head>
               <p>AN Angell from Heauen cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mightily with a loud voyce; Babilon that great Citty, it is fallen, it is fallen, and nothing ſhall inhabite there but Diuels, wilde Beaſts, and foules; becauſe all Nations haue drunken of the wine of the wrath of her forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>And there came a voyce from Heauen, ſaying, Goe out of her my people that you bee not perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of her ſinnes, and that you
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:25079:51"/>receiue not of her plagues, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde her as ſhee hath rewarded you, giue her double according to her workes, becauſe ſhee hath glorified her ſelfe and liued in pleaſure, and ſaith in her heart, I ſit being a Queene, and am no widdow, and ſhall ſee no mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: therefore ſhall her plagues come at one day, death, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and famine, and ſhe ſhall be burned with fire, for ſtrong is the Lord God which will condemne her.</p>
               <p>And the Kings that haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication with her, and the Merchants that haue beene made rich by her, and euery ſhip Maiſter, and all that occupie ſhips, and ſhip-men, ſhall ſtand a farre off for feare of her tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and cry when they ſee the ſmoake of her burning, ſaying, What Citty was like to this great Citty? and they ſhall caſt duſt on
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:25079:51"/>their foreheads, and cry, Alas, alas, the great Citty, wherein were made rich all that had ſhips on the Sea, by her coſtlineſſe; for in one hower ſhee is made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate.</p>
               <p>O heauen reioyce of her, and ye holy Apoſtles and Prophets, for God hath giuen your iudgement on her; and an Angell tooke a great Mill-ſtone and caſt it into the Sea, ſaying, With ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhall the great Citty Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon bee caſt, and bee found no more, and there ſhall bee no more Muſicke, nor Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, nor Mill heard to grinde, nor candle ſhine, nor Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes voyce bee heard there any more.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:25079:52"/>
               <head>CHAP. 19.</head>
               <p>IN this Chapter is declared the prayſing of God in Heauen and Earth for the finall deſtruction of Antichriſt, but I will firſt make an end of the deſtruction thereof.</p>
               <p>In the eleuenth verſe Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw Heauen open, and Chriſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon a white horſe, and hee was called faithfull, and hee that iudgeth and fighteth righteouſly, his face like a flame of fire, and vpon his head many Crownes, hee had a name written that none knew but himſelfe, hee was cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in a garment dipped in blood, and his name was the word of God, and the warriers in Heauen followed him vpon white hories; theſe are the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of the Goſpell, their pure white linnen is the righteouſneſſ of Chriſt: out of his mouth wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:25079:52"/>a ſharpe ſword that he might ſmite the Heathen, for hee ſhall rule them with a rodde of Iron: for hee it is that treadeth the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe of the fiercenes of Gods wrath, and hee hath a name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the King of Kings and Lord of Lords: all theſe figuratiueſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue beene ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared heeretofore.</p>
               <p>And an Angell cryed to the fowles of Heauen, theſe are the tenne Kings and their armies, to gather themſelues vnto the ſupper of the great God, to eate the fleſh of Kings, Captaines, and of mighty men, and of horſes, and of them that ſit on them, and of free-men, and of bond-men and of ſmall and of great.</p>
               <p>And the Pope, and Kings, and Warriours gathered themſelues together, to make Batraile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt that ſate vppon the Horſe, and his Soldiours; but
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:25079:53"/>the Pope the falſe Prophet that deceiued them that receiued his marke, and worſhipped him, theſe were aliue caſt into the Lake burning with fire and brimſtone, and the remnant were ſlaine with the ſword that came out of Chriſts mouth; and all the foules were filled with their fleſh, that is, the tenne Kinges, and their Captaines and Soldiours had a moſt rich and full booty of the deſtruction, and ſacking of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When <hi>Rome</hi> was deſtroyed, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> heard a great voyce of a great multitude in Heauen, ſaying, <hi>Halaluiah,</hi> that is, Praiſe the Lord, ſaluation and glory and honour, and power, bee to the Lord our God, for true and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous are his iudgements, for hee hath condemned the great Whore which did corrupt the earth with her fornication, and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:25079:53"/>hath auenged the blood of the Saints ſhed by her hand. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, they ſaid <hi>Halaluiah,</hi> and her ſmoke roſe vp for euermore, and the Elders and foure Beaſts ſaid <hi>Amen, Halaluiah:</hi> Then came a voyce out of the throne, ſaying, Praiſe our God all yee his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and a great voyce as of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters, and as thunder, ſaid, <hi>Halaluiah;</hi> for our Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath reigned, let vs bee glad and reioyce, and giue glory to him, for the marriage of Chriſt is come, and his wife, that is, the faithful, hath made herſelfe ready. This ſheweth that the Goſpel ſhall flouriſh more, when Rome and the Popedome is deſtroyed, then euer it did: And to Chriſts wife was granted that ſhee ſhould bee cloathed in pure fine and ſhining linnen, that is, in Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> was bid to write, bleſſed are they that are
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:25079:54"/>called vnto the Lambs ſupper, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Theſe words are true.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſo rauiſhed with the ioy of this viſion, that hee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped the Angell that ſhewed it; but hee forbad him, and bad him worſhip God, ſaying, I am but one of your brethren, which haue the ſpirit of Propheſie which is the teſtimony of Ieſus.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 20.</head>
               <p>IN this Chapter is declared the hiſtory of Sathan, the Authour of the firſt tenne perſecutions: but when as <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come thoſe perſecuting Idolaters, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeeth in a Viſion, that God bound the Diuell for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, that is, from generall martyring and deceiuing of the elect and choſen Children of God. Yet in this time Sathan brought
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:25079:54"/>in all popiſh blaſphemies, Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions and Idolatries, and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly perſecuted thoſe that ſtood to the puritie of the word againſt Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>The Seates that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw, and them that ſate vpon them, was Chriſt and the faithfull, and gaue Iudgement, and condemned the idolatrous and ſuperſtitious Papiſts, who theſe thouſand yeares perſecuted the faithfull.</p>
               <p>And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the ſoules of them that were perſecuted for the witneſſe of IESVS, and the word of GOD, and did not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Pope, nor had taken his marke on their fore-heads, or on their hands, and they liued and reigned with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>To ariſe from popiſh errours, ſinnes and ſuperſtitions, is the firſt reſurrection; on ſuch the ſecond death ſhall haue no power, but they ſhall bee the prieſts of God
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:25079:55"/>and Chriſt, and reigne with him for euer.</p>
               <p>After the Diuell had bin bound a thouſand yeares, from the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> as an Angell in the firſt Verſe had the key of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit, and bound Sathan, then the Pope had the key of the bottomleſſe pit, to looſe the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, as appeareth in the ninth Chapter, and when hee was looſe, hee went out to deceiue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the foure quarters of the earth. <hi>Gogge</hi> and <hi>Magogge,</hi> that is, the open and the ſecret enemies of the faithfull, which are in the ninth Chapter ſhewed to bee the Locuſts, and their tayles, that is, the popiſh Cardinals, Biſhoppes, Abbots, Fryers, and ſuch like, to gather them together to battell againſt the faithfull, and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them was infinite as the ſands of the Sea: but as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed the beloued Citie, that is,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:25079:55"/>the faithfull, fire came downe from heauen and deuoured them, that is, the Lord in his wrath deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the popedome; and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell that deceiued them, and the Pope the falſe prophet, were caſt into a Lake of fire and brimſtone, where they ſhall bee tormented day and night for euermore.</p>
               <p>After all theſe things it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied that Chriſt ſhall come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to iudgement, ſitting vpon a great white throne, from whoſe face fled away both the earth and the Sea, and their place were no more found. And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the dead both great and ſmall before God, the Bookes were opened, and another Booke was opened, which is the Booke of life, and the dead were iudged of thoſe things which were written in the Bookes: this is a Viſion according to our ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie; for Gods wiſedome is his Booke, whereby hee alwayes ſeeth
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:25079:56"/>all things that euer were, are, or ſhall bee: and Death and Hell, that is, the Diuell the cauſe of them, were caſt into the Lake of fire, which is the ſecond death, and ſo were all that were not found written in the Booke of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 21.</head>
               <p>IN theſe two laſt Chapters is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared how flouriſhing the Church ſhall be after the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Popedome vnto the end of the world. This is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the tenth Chapter and the ſecond Verſe. In that Chriſt is ſaid to ſet one foote vpon the ſea, and the other vpon the land, that all Countries ſhall confeſſe Chriſt, and hee ſhall haue of his elect in all places. As <hi>Mahomet</hi> roſe iuſt with Antichriſt in the yeare 666. ſo no doubt but the example of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:25079:56"/>the deſtruction of Rome and the Popedome, ſhall make the Turkes, Iewes, and them of other Nations, to become Chriſtians. This is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared likewiſe in the 19. Chapter. Let vs be glad and reioyce for the deſtruction of Rome, becauſe then the Lambs wife ſhall be made rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and bleſſed are they that are called vnto the Lambes Supper.</p>
               <p>In that there ſhall bee then a new heauen, meaning the Church; and a new earth, meaning tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gouernment, and the old is paſſed away, it ſheweth, that things touching the Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth ſhall bee wholly ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led according vnto the Word of God, and that all Popiſh and Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh lawes which are contrary to the Word of GOD ſhall bee no more.</p>
               <p>And there ſhall be no more ſea, that is, ignorant and vnconſtant men carryed away with euery wind
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:25079:57"/>of falſe doctrine, as the waues of the ſea are toſſed with the winde.</p>
               <p>Then the Church ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared as a fit Bride for Chriſt her husband, that is, the Tabernacle of God ſhall bee with men, and GOD ſhall dwell with them, and they ſhall bee his people, and God himſelfe ſhall be their God, and wipe away all teares from their eyes, and there ſhall bee no more death, ſorrow, crying or paine, for the firſt things are paſt, that is, then there ſhall bee no more martyring, perſecuting, moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, blaſpheming and deriding of Gods Children.</p>
               <p>In the tenth Verſe an Angell ſhewes Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> a Viſion of the glory that the Church then ſhall haue. In that it is called a great Citie, it ſhewes what a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſhall beleeue: in that it is called holy Ieruſalem, it declareth the holineſſe of their Faith, Hope and
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:25079:57"/>Loue, and other graces: the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending of it from God out of heauen, ſheweth that God from heauen, ſhall fill her with the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his graces: and ſhee had the glory of God, which made her ſhine like precious ſtones.</p>
               <p>The three gates on euery ſide, are the Trinitie, without which there is no way to enter into the Church: the Angels that are at theſe doores, are the Preachers: the twelue foundations of this Church, is Ieſus Chriſt, which the twelue Apoſtles haue taught vs to build all our hope vpon: in that the three gates were on euery ſide of the Church, it ſheweth that the doores of grace ſhall lye open, and the Goſpell be preached vnto all nations.</p>
               <p>The twelue thouſand furlongs, the length, the bredth, and the height of it, haue an alluſion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the twelue thouſand of euery
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:25079:58"/>Tribe that were marked for God in the ſeauenth Chapter: the wals being, an hundred forty foure cubits, haue an alluſion vnto the hundred forty foure thouſand, the whole number of them that were marked of all Tribes.</p>
               <p>The ſtones of the wall ſignifie the faithfull: in that they are preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, it is by reaſon that the precious righteouſneſſe of Ieſus Chriſt is imputed vnto them, and of their precious Faith, Hope and Loue, and other graces giuen them of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In that they are a wall to the new Ieruſalem, that the Diuell nor any vncleane thing can come into it, is declared how louingly they ſhall ioyne one with another as ſtones in a wall, and how ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſhall ſupport one another, to expell and to keepe out falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and to defend the truth.</p>
               <p>In that this Citie was of pure
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:25079:58"/>gold, it ſheweth the puritie of their Religion, without any droſſe of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions.</p>
               <p>In that there was no Temple, it ſheweth, that they ſhall truely ſerue God in ſpirit and truth, and Chriſt ſhall bee their Temple, in whom all their hearts ſhall meet, and in him offer all ſacrifices of prayer and prayſing of God, and of good workes, which the Lord will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept for his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
               <p>In that it hath no neede of the Sunne nor of the Moone to ſhine in it, the holy Spirit ſhall ſo illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate their vnderſtandings more then the light of naturall reaſon can teach them: and there ſhall be no night: for where the ſpirit of God is, there is no darkneſſe.</p>
               <p>In that the gates ſhall neuer bee ſhut, it certifieth, that none that come with a liuely faith ſhall bee ſhut from Grace, and that Grace
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:25079:59"/>ſhall alwayes bee offered.</p>
               <p>In that the glory and the honor of the Gentiles ſhall bee brought vnto it, it ſheweth that the Kings and chiefeſt of all Countries ſhall beleeue in Chriſt: and there ſhall enter into it no vncleane thing, that is, wicked men; nor whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer worketh abhomination and lyes, ſuch they ſhall hate and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate: but onely ſuch ſhall enter as are written in the Lambes Booke of life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 22.</head>
               <p>THe pure riuer of water of life, like Chryſtall, proceeding out of the Throne, is the doctrine of the Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer drinketh of him ſhall neuer thirſt for any other meanes of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: their thirſt ſhall bee ſo fully quenched in him, that they ſhall alwayes reioyce in their ſaluation. Hee is the tree of life, whoſoeuer eateth of him with a liuely Faith
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:25079:59"/>ſhall haue eternall life, and he ſhall neuer hunger, that is, doubt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Chriſt alwayes is fruitfull, and the leaues of his righteouſnes ſhall heale the imperfections and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the faithfull in all nations.</p>
               <p>There ſhall bee no curſe, but the throne of God and the Lambe ſhall be amongſt the faithfull, and they ſhall be his ſeruants and ſerue him, and they ſhall ſee his face, and his name ſhall be written in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads, that is, they ſhall not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to confeſſe his name, and they ſhall reigne for euermore, that is, in the world to come.</p>
               <p>Then S. <hi>Iohn</hi> concludes the truth of theſe Propheſies by the Angels teſtimony and his owne: and laſtly, hee bringeth in Ieſus Chriſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for the teſtimony of the truth hereof; I Ieſus haue ſent mine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to teſtifie theſe things in the Churches, I am the roote and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of <hi>Dauid,</hi> the bright mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:25079:60"/>Starre. The Spirit &amp; the Bride exhort men to come to me, and let euery one that heares exhort men to come to mee; and let all that thirſt, and will take of the water of life freely, come: for I proteſt that who ſo ſhall adde any thing to this Booke, God will adde to him the plagues written in this Booke: and if any diminiſh of the words here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, God will take away his part out of the Booke of life, and the holy Citie: he that teſtifieth theſe things ſaith, Surely I come quickly, <hi>Amen,</hi> Euen ſo Lord Ieſus. The grace of our Lord Ieſus be with vs all, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:25079:60"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
